[ominous music playing]
[tools grinding. whirring]
You said you knew where she was going.
- I did. She got away.
- From you.
She was helped
by one of her Mechanical friends.
I chased them.
but they got down here first
and disappeared
before I could get a chair.
You already knew I was down here.
People take notice
of where you go. Robert.
You know what?
I'll-I'll take it from here.
I know Greasetown. And it's still on edge.
I've got Jo and Chad.
I think I can manage.
I should be here for you.
- We could split up.
- Go home to Anthony.
Spend time with him.
It doesn't have to come to that.
It will if I can't find her.
Camille Sims for Emerson.
I'm below the gap.
When Nichols was a fugitive.
she was caught down here.
Find out where.
Oh. and Judge Sims is headed up.
Keep eyes on him...
- for his safety.
- [Emerson] Copy that.
[Bernard breathing heavily]
[groans] I need to lie down.
[grunts] Have some water.
The actual fuck? You're alive?
He's alive?
- [Bernard sighs]
- Here.
Anybody else coming back from the dead?
The old sheriff. maybe his wife?
Did anybody see you?
Just Teddy.
[gulps. sighs]
Mr. Kyle.
Mr. Holland.
I'm very glad you're still alive.
[scoffs]
I didn't think you'd survive the move.
Isn't there a small part of you
that's happy to see me again?
[door opens]
[pants] I remember.
I know what we have to do.
Emerson for Camille Sims.
- Go.
- The address you were looking for
is a workshop on 144.
occupied by Martha Walker.
One of the lines must have been a pipe.
What?
Mr. Kyle put the hard drive I smashed
back together.
The-The diagram you found
showed lines coming in from outside.
There are two lines. One goes to IT.
and the other goes to Judicial.
And I didn't know what the lines were.
but that's why I went to the mines.
[Kennedy] Yeah. well. you're an idiot.
They're not gonna put some killer pipe
where criminals dig all day.
There are tunnels in the mines
that go up and down the Silo.
And I almost made it
to the line that goes into IT
when they gassed the mines.
The lines going into IT
carry electricity from Silo 1.
So if the generator stops
there's always power in IT.
So. then the line that goes to Judicial.
th-that's the Safeguard.
I think that's what he said. That's...
- I think that's what Jimmy said.
- Now hold on. who is Jimmy?
Jimmy is the guy that I was with in 17.
That's what... I think that's what he said.
Did this Jimmy tell you
where the lines entered into Judicial?
[Juliette] He had an old blueprint. but...
No. It... I can't... [stammering] It's gone.
Where's our blueprint?
Look. if we have a blueprint.
it would be on that hard drive
which is back in IT.
We're not gonna get to that.
Well. maybe your new pal. Sims.
can help us find it.
Where is Sims?
He went to head off Camille.
Wait. Is 17 the same as our silo?
Yeah. they're exactly the same.
So. then if we find the pipe in 17.
we find it here.
Is there a way to communicate with Jimmy?
Every silo has its own frequency.
so I can try to...
I never saw him with a radio.
I never found a radio. I...
Camille Sims is coming this way.
[Bernard] Oh. shit.
- We're gonna have to move you again.
- [grunts]
- Go.
- Shit.
[Hank] You serious?
How long do we have?
[Paul] McLain said
when she became Head of Supply
we had 70 years of light bulbs left.
Since someone started stealing them.
it's down to two.
What do we do?
First. we keep this to ourselves.
It's only been three months
since one rebellion.
we can't have another one.
Then we find out who killed Orla Kent.
When we do. we might find out
who stole the light bulbs.
Or if we find out who's
been stealing light bulbs.
maybe we find out who killed Orla Kent.
[tense music plays]
Before you arrest me. we should talk.
Somewhere with no cameras.
[whispers] I remember everything.
- Oh. fuck.
- Fuck what?
[stammers] We're now going 70.
We probably should have tried to jump out
when we were still in the city.
I said that. and then you said
that we would die even at 40.
Only horribly injured.
But now. we'd definitely just be a smear.
Can you just... Can you just try
taking out the key? Please.
No.
- Hey. What?
- If we get the fob away from the van.
- won't it just stop working?
- I hope not.
Your kid tosses it.
and you shut down in the middle of I-95?
Not safe.
Safe is not what
I'm fucking feeling right now.
[sighs] No brakes. No steering.
This is like what
happened to Charlotte's squadron.
You think someone in Iran is driving this?
I don't know. but someone is.
Stensen's been sounding the alarm
on how AI can be used by hackers. right?
So maybe he was on the Nimitz
because he feared
the planes would be compromised.
And they were.
Too crazy?
[sighs] I think we're neck-deep in crazy.
[sighs]
I need something with a flat edge.
[Helen] Damn it.
Uh. [sighs]
Here.
[breathing heavily]
- Do you actually know what you're doing?
- [exhales sharply]
Uh. roughly. Brakes are simple.
You step on a pedal. it activates a line
which makes the brake pads squeeze.
But whoever's... [stammers] ...driving this.
is doing something
with the electronics to stop that.
So. if I can access the... [grunts]
- What?
- Fuck!
[breathes heavily]
Damn it.
Oh.
Let me see.
Think you'll live?
Sure hope so.
I know about the voice.
- What voice?
- No. don't do that.
I'm not gonna talk to you about this.
Camille. you know I didn't go
into a refuge hut.
I don't know what it tells you.
but I went into another silo.
Hmm.
It's not dead. There are kids in it.
And they're alone. and somehow
they've managed to survive.
But I promised them
that I would go back to them.
That's what I remember.
I remember that I said
I would bring them back here.
- That's an insane request.
- Let me ask the voice. and it can decide.
No.
You know people treat me
like a living Founder.
If I jump off the stairs. they'll follow.
You wanna see what else
they're willing to do for me?
You sound like a threat to the Silo.
No. Camille. I want to save the kids.
[device buzzing]
You sure there are no cameras here?
It looks like it knows we're talking.
[buzzing continues]
- Any luck?
- No.
[sighs] There has to be some way
to stop this thing.
- Oh. oh!
- What?
Hey. hey. hey. hey. hey!
Hey! Stop! Call the police!
Help. help. help. help!
Stop. stop. stop. stop!
Please. please. please!
Call the police! Stop! Hey!
What the fuck?
What happened?
I think I know how to stop this thing.
Hank. I make things. I don't steal them.
We're just hoping
you know somebody who does.
I only associate
with Pact-abiding citizens. you know that.
Mark. we... we've got something
pretty serious going on.
We could really use your help.
Serious. like getting chucked
over the rail?
There are two raiders guilty of throwing
my best friend to his death
during the rebellion.
But I don't hear you asking about that.
This friend of yours.
was his name Lee Torgenson?
And was he thrown over
for using a weapon you made for him?
- Oh. fuck you. Who the fuck are you?
- I'm the sheriff.
- And if you don't cooperate. we...
- You're not a sheriff.
- You're an accident.
- [Hank] Mark.
You got the job by default.
Now you're standing here
wearing Holston's hand-me-downs.
and they're one size too big.
You wanna arrest someone?
- Arrest your wife.
- Mark!
You think people don't know
about her and the Outsiders?
Trying to get us all killed?
Oh. What are you going to do. Mr. Sheriff?
Drag me out of here?
That'll look great.
[Hank] Mark. we are not threatening you.
We're just in a tough spot.
and we really need to know
if anyone has info on things
disappearing from Critical Supply.
I'm not doing shit for this asshole.
How about this...
You give us something we can use.
and I'll look into the raiders.
- You won't do anything...
- I'll get their names.
I'll give them to you. Whatever you do
with that information is up to you.
All right.
Here's this...
The weapons I made. I made for Knox.
You wanna know about stolen shit?
His father was crooked as a screw.
He used to steal
diamond drill bits from Supply.
and sold 'em on the black market
as jewelry.
Far as I know. he's out of that game.
But he'll know more than I will.
That something you can use?
Get me those names.
- You all right?
- I'm fine.
[Helen] We just sit. and we wait. [sighs]
Come on. [stammers]
All it takes is one person
to see an empty van driving by itself.
and they will call the cops.
Oh. ye of little faith.
[device chimes]
[door closes]
[The Algorithm]
Juliette Nichols. why are you here?
You just speak.
Okay. Um...
I know what happened when I went outside.
And... In Silo 17 there are kids.
and I want to bring them back. Here.
Silo 17 is flooding.
a-and they're gonna die.
I'm not working against the Silo.
I'm not working against you.
I'm not a threat.
[The Algorithm] The numbers predict
disaster for the Silo if you leave.
Request is denied.
No. not me.
We'll send someone else to get them.
[The Algorithm]
The numbers predict disaster
if residents from another silo
join Silo 18.
Request is denied.
No. but they're kids.
They're gonna die in 17.
[The Algorithm] They'd be invasive.
Request is denied.
Time to leave. Come on.
Okay. what if I go back on
the memory drug? Is that what you want?
I'll do it.
You can even drug the kids.
And then they won't be a threat
to anyone here. right?
[Juliette breathes shakily]
[The Algorithm] How many children?
[door closes]
I think you're making a play.
- I'm not.
- You're not?
- You have my word.
- I have your word. really?
You lied to me.
You drugged me for three fucking months.
and you question my honesty?
I'll find someone to get the kids.
and then I'll go back to being your mayor.
[tires screeching]
[sighs]
What?
We're in the middle of fucking nowhere.
[sighs]
Don't rental cars have.
like... locator things?
I got this from Joe's sketchy car rental.
There's no locator.
[sighs]
You're a congressman.
so people are gonna notice
if you don't show up for work.
[chuckling] Not for at least a day.
They'll just be glad I'm not babbling
about infrastructure reform.
What about Charlotte?
[sighs] Saw her a couple of days ago.
she barely knew who I was.
And Crnkovich asked me
to stay away for a little bit
while she gets focused therapy.
But. he said she is doing better. so...
There's that.
You? Any. uh. potential rescuers
in your corner?
[sighs] I mean...
I got fired. so... [chuckles] ...nobody there
is expecting to see me ever again.
And I am a pretty shitty friend.
It takes me weeks to call anyone back.
So. no.
- Hmm.
- Hmm?
- You know...
- What?
If they did just want to kill us.
they've had plenty of opportunities.
They could have driven us
into a bridge abutment
or off a cliff. or into a tree.
But they haven't. which. you know.
leaves the possibility
we could be going someplace nice.
[chuckles]
We are so fucked.
[door unlocks]
Where's Lukas and Kennedy?
Kennedy just wouldn't stop talking.
He needs a rest. so. I found them
an empty single down the hallway.
- Good.
- Where did you go?
I went with Camille.
[whispering] To the Vault.
I. um... I spoke to it.
What did you say?
I said I wanna send two people to 17.
and bring the kids back here.
And it believed you?
I think so.
- Is it a person. or a machine?
- I don't know. Um.
So who you gonna send?
You know. when I went out
I didn't have a choice.
I had to keep going. Right?
There are... There are hundreds.
There are thousands of bodies out there.
So. whoever we send have
to be able to walk through that.
and not wanna turn back.
If I had the choice.
I don't think I could do it.
So. they better be strong.
Yeah.
And they've gotta be smart.
They've gotta find that pipe.
They've gotta figure out how to cap it.
They need to be engineers.
The best you have.
[sighs]
Ask.
They can always say no.
Shirl. what's going on?
- Why don't you sit down?
- No. it's...
I can't stop thinking
all of us could be gone.
Before we ever get a chance to...
[Knox] I know.
But we can't think like that.
We just have to focus on...
on what we can do.
Knox.
I need a word with you.
About what?
Your father.
This is not a good time.
Yeah. it'll just take a minute.
What do you know about his connection
to the market in stolen goods?
I'm not doing this right now.
- Why not?
- 'Cause I'm not.
Are you trying to protect him?
Are you fucking kidding me?
Are you really asking me that?
- Yes. I am because if you are...
- [Knox] What?
What are you gonna do?
- You think that badge means shit to me?
- Hank.
[stammers] All right. Just-Just calm down.
All right?
This is about a murder.
- Who?
- Orla Kent.
- I don't know her.
- The hell you don't.
She was the shadow to the head of Supply.
She was at the Silo Council...
If I say I don't her.
then I don't fucking know her.
Like you apparently don't know me.
Get him the fuck out of here. Hank.
- Move. Let me the fuck at...
- [Hank] No.
Leave it. Just. don't.
Not now. Just. trust me. Not now.
Trust me.
Hey. Look. you told me Harwood
had a run-in with Orla Kent
at the Council meeting.
- [Paul breathing heavily]
- Right? You said McLain was suspicious
of Harwood's daughter
when she was shadowing her...
- Glenda.
- Yeah.
Already spoke to her.
Got nothing concrete.
But maybe we can track her movements.
And Orla's.
Track them?
H-How?
[door opens]
What do you want?
Where do you watch the cameras?
Nowhere.
[inhales. exhales]
There was a room on 19.
but they've shut it down.
I've been rewriting the Pact.
and I know nothing's changed.
Take us.
[Martha] What is that?
There was a relic I kept in my pocket for...
years. [inhales sharply]
Records said that it was found
in a pillowcase a long time ago.
They called such things...
good luck charms.
Well. did it work?
Well. the relic burned
along with some of me. so maybe not.
That said. I'm still alive.
Although. I'm not sure that's good luck.
Oh. boo-hoo.
You're being waited on hand and foot.
All you have to do
is lie back and pontificate.
[breathes heavily]
Why did you keep me alive?
[sighs] You convinced Sims
not to kill Juliette.
[Bernard] Oh. I know.
It's just...
It can't have been easy.
No.
And you're still a ratshit asshole.
You shouldn't be surprised
if you wake up one morning
with a screwdriver in your neck.
Even as a boy they wanted me dead.
[chuckles]
That wasn't a joke.
I was always...
too smart and... [sighs]
...too quiet. [chuckles]
[chuckles]
What's so amusing?
[stammers] It's just...
It's just something Carla said.
She said if I liked men.
and you liked people.
we'd make a great couple.
That is amusing.
[Martha chuckles]
[chuckles]
I wanted to apologize.
Now you don't?
It's the wrong tense.
If you actually want to apologize.
it's "I want..."
I want... want to apologize.
Present tense.
For what I said about journalistic fraud.
What happened?
You really didn't look it up?
I just saw there was some thing
at the Post.
"Thing at the Post" makes it sound like
I wore white to a wedding.
I started to read it. and then...
You made something up.
[clicks tongue. inhales sharply]
I did a piece on drug addiction
among congressional staffers.
Yeah. Uh. I was careful.
I changed everyone's details
'cause I knew people would try
and read between the lines.
And I wanted to protect my sources.
Protect their anonymity...
but the day it was published.
a quote from a young woman
I called Sharon got everybody talking.
I knew it would.
She implied that drug use
was not limited to staffers.
Rumors... [sighs] ...you know. spread
that the Speaker was using.
You can imagine the pressure
to reveal Sharon's identity.
Legislators. prosecutors.
Capitol police. all...
demanding I reveal her real name.
And then those fuck-nuts at
the Washingtonian published a piece saying
Sharon was really Gillian Aikens
who worked in the Speaker's office.
Mm-hmm.
Problem was they were right.
So what did you do?
Only thing I could do.
I published a tearful confession.
said I'd heard some
utterly spurious rumors about the Speaker.
and had made up Sharon.
You gave up your career
to protect a source?
I gave up my career
because I failed Gillian.
If I'd done a better job...
her name would have never come up.
[sighs]
- No.
- Hmm?
What?
You're not going to 17.
I'll go alone.
You can't go alone. No one can.
- Why not?
- In case one of us doesn't make it.
Then... [stammers] ...Teddy will come with me.
Jules. could you just give us a second?
I need to make a move.
It won't take long.
I'll tell her.
And if I do that. she'll never let...
You tell her. and I raise this kid alone.
[Knox sighs]
We don't do this. our kid
and everyone in here will never be safe.
Shirl. please.
Let me take someone else.
- It's not the same.
- [breathes heavily]
You know that.
If you were Jules. who would you send?
Hmm?
Fuck!
[Shirley sighs]
It has to be us.
Both of us.
We do this...
and something happens to you.
[stammers] Something happens...
It's different now. I don't...
I don't know if I'd come back from that.
When we were on our way up
to see the judge.
you said you wanted
to go out to see the distance.
At least we'll see it together.
You have to promise me.
if I go down. you just keep going.
You don't stop. You don't...
You don't try and save me.
You just go.
[Shirley sighs]
We'll do it.
Okay.
[door opens]
[door closes]
What's wrong?
You wanna tell her?
Your son stole 12 credits
out of his teacher's desk today.
Another boy saw him.
When confronted by the teacher.
Anthony blamed it on someone else.
[Camille] Anthony Aaron Sims.
What do you have to say for yourself?
I'm gonna need more than that.
School says if it happens again.
he'll be expelled
and sent to work in Supply.
Anthony. go to your room.
Now!
Supply?
[Sims] I'm Judge.
You're head of IT.
Doubt if it'll actually happen.
[Camille] That's your solution?
Use our positions to fix it?
- It's not what I said.
- [Camille] No.
No. of course not. I have to read
between the lines like always.
- Meaning?
- [Camille sighs]
You're avoiding the problem.
I went to the school.
I talked to the principal.
I apologized to the teacher.
What am I avoiding?
Don't do that. Don't guilt-trip me.
If you feel guilt. it's not my fault.
Are we still talking about Anthony?
I'm not sure.
Are we?
You need to stop
everything you've been doing.
You've been watchin' me.
You think I can't spot a tail?
You're making me afraid. Rob.
For our son.
For our family.
Because whatever you're hiding.
when I find out what it is...
I'm gonna have to do something about it.
[door opens]
[breathing heavily] Hmm.
- [Helen] Hmm?
- You. uh... Um...
Well. you kept the PEZ.
Didn't even know I had it.
- Really?
- [Helen] Mmm.
- Wasn't a memento?
- No.
Something to help you remember
the world's worst blind date?
- It wasn't a date.
- [Daniel] Oh.
Right.
- [vehicle approaches]
- [siren blares]
Shit.
- Oh. my God.
- [Daniel] You were right.
I honestly didn't think we had
a hope in hell.
They're not stopping us.
Because they don't want to.
They're our escort.
[keypad beeps]
I think it's a mistake.
Hello?
You there?
[The Algorithm] What is a mistake?
[stammers] Allowing Juliette
to send someone to Silo 17.
She's after more than the children.
If there are any children.
You don't know. do you?
[The Algorithm] Whether or not there are
children in Silo 17 does not matter.
How? How-How does it not matter?
[The Algorithm] You're not
really interested in an answer.
You are looking for an argument.
I will not engage.
Fuck off.
[The Algorithm] Your heart rate
and respiration are elevated.
[scoffs] Okay.
I feel Juliette is a threat to the Silo.
My husband is lying to me.
and my son is a thief.
All of that...
All of that is on me.
[stammers] As head of IT.
as a wife. as a mother.
And...
I'm failing.
[clears throat]
Fuck.
[The Algorithm]
I'm sorry you feel that way.
- but thoughts aren't facts.
- [sighs]
That sense of failure is the result
of being emotionally exhausted.
You need to find a moment
for yourself. To reflect.
Yeah.
[sighs]
I don't know how.
[The Algorithm] You've already started
by acknowledging your negative thoughts.
Your breathing has started to normalize.
You were chosen for a difficult job
because you are capable.
Take time
to remind yourself of that. Camille.
It is not a job just anyone can do.
Thank you.
[sighs]
[door opens]
You're not supposed to be in here.
This place is not in the Pact.
so there is no here.
Out.
[door opens]
Supposed to be
only a few cameras left for security.
Someone lied.
Move.
[door closes]
Orla Kent's body was found
in the mines two days ago.
Right after the gas.
Show me the mines right before that.
There's no cameras in the mines.
I'm sure there's one at the entrance.
Keep going. Further back.
Look. you're gonna see
the extermination team go in.
with the miners inside.
Why?
They were tryna flush out Lukas Kyle.
You gassed the mines?
I was following orders.
Show us.
[breathes shakily] Wait.
Stop.
No. that's Glenda Harwood.
We need Orla Kent.
Show us the stairs. ten levels down.
[exhales] See Orla?
[Hank] Nothing.
[breathes heavily]
Show us Supply at the same time.
[stammers] No. Wait. Stop. What's...
Is that Glenda?
- Wasn't she just in the mines?
- Is this at the same time?
Yeah. the same ten minutes.
How did Glenda get
from the mines to Supply in ten minutes?
I don't know.
It won't let you send them.
I need to send people
who can get shit done.
That's Knox and that's Shirley.
That's why they can't go.
They're needed here.
Choose someone expendable.
But for the kids
to be able to make it back.
I need to send Knox and Shirley.
It can't be Knox and Shirley.
The voice gave me permission.
That's nice.
but until it grows a pair of arms
and learns how to walk.
I'm the one who opens the door.
Choose someone else.
Okay. Let's send. um. Kennedy and Lukas.
You know where they are?
- [Juliette] Yeah.
- Where?
Well. considering you want them dead.
I'm not gonna tell you.
Considering you want them dead.
you won't mind sending them out.
- [tools grinding. whirring]
- [workers yelling indistinctly]
That thing earlier with Billings?
Kind of intense.
Yeah. he's an asshole.
I meant your reaction
when he mentioned your father.
My father's an asshole too.
So you gonna tell me?
He was never around.
I mean. maybe you'll remember growing up...
it was just me and my mom.
And it was hard. We struggled.
Never enough food.
I never had... [chuckles] ...clothes that fit.
I remember when I was a little kid.
I wanted one of those.
uh... those Freedom Day lanterns.
I wanted one so bad.
Couldn't afford it.
But we were okay.
'Cause my mom...
she worked her ass off.
Somehow she still...
she still made time for me.
I don't know when she slept. [chuckles]
Where was your dad?
The mines.
He was supposedly a great engineer.
but he was always in trouble
for breaking the Pact.
Trading stolen goods mostly I think.
But the truth is. he just loved that life.
More than he loved us.
Thing is.
him being gone wasn't the problem.
The problem was when he came home.
He'd turn up
after a stint in the mines. full of it.
Always tryna start shit with my mom.
He would fuck our lives up.
Then he'd get arrested.
and be gone again. [chuckles]
And the cycle would repeat.
I haven't seen him in years.
Thanks for telling me.
But. uh... [inhales]
Now you've gotten it off your chest.
go help Billings.
A girl's been murdered.
You might be able to help.
Thanks for coming. Asa.
- I have a choice?
- [chuckles]
IT has detected low instances
of Vitamin D.
We need to add a boost
to the water supply.
Okay. [sighs. clears throat]
You'll need to turn off
the osmosis filtration system
before we add it.
- Uh...
- Is there a problem?
[Ed] Okay. shit-heels.
Eyes on me.
You're not here because you stole.
or cheated. or broke the Pact.
You're here because you were too stupid
to get away with it.
Word of advice.
Do not try and be stupid in here
because if you do.
you'll end up buried
under a ton of dirt and stone.
Your days of being stupid are over.
Mr. Gunton here
will set you up with tools.
So. yeah. that's it.
Fuck off.
[murmuring]
What are you doing here?
I need to talk with my father.
You bring a shovel?
He died two years ago.
[keypad beeping]
[The Algorithm] Hello. Juliette Nichols.
have you chosen your candidates?
I have.
Deagan Knox
and Shirley Campbell from Mechanical.
Go on. run the numbers.
[The Algorithm] The request is denied.
Their absence would increase risk
to Silo life by 34%.
No. I need it to be them.
[The Algorithm] Please submit alternates.
I don't have any.
Hello? Is that... Is that it?
Yeah. I guess we should go.
Lukas Kyle and Patrick Kennedy.
- [The Algorithm] You know where they are?
- She does.
She won't say.
[The Algorithm] Approved.
Send them out tomorrow at dawn.
You may go.
I still think bringing those children here
is a mistake.
[The Algorithm] Wait one moment.
Lukas Kyle and Patrick Kennedy
will never make it to Silo 17.
I don't...
Did you just play Juliette?
[The Algorithm] Juliette Nichols requires...
special handling.
Even if there are children alive in 17.
she may still have another objective.
You need to introduce Vitamin D+
into the water supply as soon as possible.
With Nichols's memory back...
She'll infect everyone around her.
I realize that.
But if everyone forgets who she is.
she won't matter anymore.
Vitamin D+ entered
the water system two hours ago.
[doors unlock]
[door lock clicks]
Daniel.
Helen.
How'd you like to help save the world?